<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An history briefly contayninge that whiche hath happened sens the departure of the house of Guise the constable, and other from the court being at S. Germanis, vntill the present.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68120</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847705</idno>
  <idno type="VID">12761</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248523391</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 12507</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S112451</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99847705e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12761)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:10, 463:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An history briefly contayninge that whiche hath happened sens the departure of the house of Guise the constable, and other from the court being at S. Germanis, vntill the present.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Seres,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1562?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An anonymous translation.</note>
                  <note>Imprint and suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 11277.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11277 on UMI microfilm reel 241.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at UMI microfilm reels 241 and 463.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Charles IX, 1560-1574 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:1"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London in Powles Churchyarde by Richarde Iugge printer to the Quenes Maiestie.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegiō Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:1"/>
            <p>¶ An History briefly contayninge that whiche hath happened sens the departure of the house of <hi>Guise,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, and other from the Court being at <hi>S. Germanis,</hi> vntill this present.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAYE THE XLV.</bibl> ¶ Cursed be he that resisteth his maker.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>1562.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VV. S.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:2"/>
            <head>¶ An Historye briefelye contayninge that whiche hath happened sens the departure of the house of Guise the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, and others from the Court being at S. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis vntill this present.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ESAYE THE XLV.</bibl>
               <q>¶ Cursed be he that resisteth his maker.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queene ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing according to her accustomed goodnes) accepte the charge of the gouernemente of thys Realme, offered vnto her by the Estates, and by the consent &amp; motion of the king of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre, and my Lordes his brethren, &amp; Cousins, the Princes of the blood: doing therin the office of a mother, aswell towardes the Kynge, as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes her subiectes, hath well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb facs="tcp:12761:3"/>that she had nothing more to harte, then to geue order touchinge the troubles and tumultes risinge by meanes of religion: Not hauing ceassed to find out through her wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and carefulnes, all the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and meanes, that haue bene thought diuisable to this effect. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that she hadde knowen by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples past, that the rigor of lawes, and streict execuiton coulde doe no good, and contrariwise that thashes of one burned did reise by an infinit number of others, of the same opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and like constancye, and that also it was not sittynge to the age nor disposicion of a yong Prince, to begynne his reigne by shedinge of blood, and hauing sithens likewise followed and executed the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions agreed vppon, in the late time of kinge Fraunces the laste at Fountainebarn whiche was to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble all those which would come to make anye demonstration tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the maner of religion, and to deuyse if that by anye meane of conference, the saide troubles and sturres might be brought to an end: and hauing lastely left nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done
<pb facs="tcp:12761:3"/>whyche myghte serue to the common quiet and tranquilitye, she hath bene constrained in thende (to appease these vprores) to take the remedy of the Edict made in Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary last, in loking for the end of the generall counsaile, to satisfy by this meanes (at the lestwise in some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye) the very earnest complainct and request of thestates of this Realme.</p>
            <p>And albeit by meanes of the son, the Quene had geuen all men great occasion of contentacion, hauing fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed therin thaduise of the moste notable and piked companye out of all the Courtes of Parlamente of this Realme, and hauing therin ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued all the solemnite, that coulde be wyshed, yet neuertheles some (of whom we will speake herafter) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not wel pleased for some other cause (as indede it is harde to please euery man) they determined to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the executiō of thedict, by al the meanes they coulde, together with this determinacion of the Queene, hauinge taken weapon in hande, came to be about the kinges person and the Quenes, aucthorizing them selues with their Princes, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb facs="tcp:12761:4"/>the kinge of Nauarres auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, against my Lord the Prince of Condee, who desirous on the other side to maintayne that whiche was graunted to thestates, did also arme himselfe to stay their rage and fury, and to resist the same to his power. And forasmuch as many may be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt of the particuler dyscourse of this tumulte, and speciallye the causes and reasons that maye haue moued and may moue thone partye and thother, I thought I shuld do a thing no lesse acceptable then profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, to set them forth, &amp; giue them trulye tunderstande to all men and specially to them which are minded to serue and feight on thone side or thother, to the ende that the playne trueth of the thynge knowne to all menne, euerye one maye the better iudge whiche side of the twoo, hath moost reason with them, and is best grounded for the cause of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery into armes.</p>
            <p>These shall be to let them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that the Quene being readye to assemble a good &amp; notable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of presidentes and counsellors, out of all the parlamentes of thys
<pb facs="tcp:12761:4"/>Realme, to consult vppon some ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary remedy, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ceasing of the troubles, and answering the request of the states, desiring very instantly to haue Churches appointed them. The house of Gwyse beganne to murmure and saye, that they sawe wel, that the matter wolde come to and Interim, and by thys meanes abolishe the religion of the Church of Roome, and that this was not the meanes to slake and lay downe the troubles, which (they saide) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaded not but of the sufferaunce of those who gaue so easy entry to the Heretiques, to plant and sow here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syes, and throughe the neglygence and bearinge of the Maiestrates and Ministers of Iustice, and so procea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge further, beganne by coulora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble termes, to blayme the Queene for her ouermuch softnes, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accuse the kynge of Nauarre (who truelye hathe bene one that hath asmuche holpen to plant, and set forwarde the Religyon in thys Realme, as presently vnder his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye some do assaye to reuoque and supplant the same) &amp; my lordes hys brethren, and other Prynces
<pb facs="tcp:12761:5"/>of the blood, in blaminge their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of gouernment, and castinge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theym all the faulte, euen as thoughe the troubles had not bene stirred before this kinges raigne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng further, that if the wayes to roote out heresyes, holden by the Kynges heretofore, had bene follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, that they should not haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into these inconueniences, and that thonely remedy had bene to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue theim, &amp; to obserue Thedict, made in Iuly last before to driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all the Mynysters, and not to permitte any more assemblyes, and that it should haue bene easy by this meanes, to cause tholde religion, to be kept vpright, &amp; that therefore se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing al thinges proceade contrary to their mindes, they hadde rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Court (as indede they did,) about thend of Nouember last past giuing men clerely tunderstand their discontentacion, which within few dayes after increased sumwhat more; by meanes of the processe, made against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Duke de Nemours, stirred vppe by theym, to go aboute the taking and conueyinge awaye with him by force, the Duke of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leauns,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:5"/>and so hauyng him at the deuocion to make him the heade of their enterprise wherof we wil here no further intreat.</p>
            <p>And now that the Duke of Guise and his brethren were departed the Courte, they began euen furthwith to practise by all the meanes they coulde, to bringe their pourposes to passe, whiche was to retourne with greater fauour &amp; aucthoriti, then (as they thought) they departed thens.</p>
            <p>And takynge the title of religion, they assay, to win and draw to their partye (by thelp of the Popes Legat (Madame de Guise vncle) the King of Nauarre &amp; the Constable. Which thei in thēd easely brought to passe, that is to say, the kyng of Nauarre, by inducinge of him into a vayne hope, to be agayne inuested in hys kyngdom of Nauarre. And that the Pope should recompence the kynge of spaine, so that the sayde kynge of Nauarre woulde mayntayne the Church of Rome, and the said Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, by the meanes of a matter in compremise touching a controuersy betwene them concerninge the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Lordeship of Dampmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn
<pb facs="tcp:12761:6"/>to whom also it was proponed, that if this religion (which is called new) toke place, that the same shuld be a planke to steppe ryght vpon, to the request made by thestates, which was to thende that the sayde house of Guise, he himselfe, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal S. Andre, and others should be called vpon to giue accoumpt of the exceading large giftes receyued by thē of the treasure of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Realme ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by to helpe to discharge the king of his deptes, which matter also serued to pourpose to bring in to them the Mareshall S. Andre, beinge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse drawē therto by the Cardynal of Turnon, whiche also was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, besydes other matters whyche the tyme may discouer.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus deuised their plat, thei ceassed not to sollicite the Kinge of Nauarre, to declare himselfe to bee for the pope. The king of Nauarre, began euen furthwith openlye and before all the worlde, to shewe that he woulde mainteine the Romyshe religion, he droue away from about him the Ministers, he goth to Masse to the mooste notable Churches of Paris, goeth about to constraine by
<pb facs="tcp:12761:6"/>all meanes the Quene of Nauarre, and my Lord the Prince, his sonne, to go thither also: and to be short, there is nothinge that he doeth not.</p>
            <p>And albeit that he was preuye at the making of the Edict set furth in Ianuarie, and likewise allowed the same, notwithstandinge he was so sollicited &amp; practised, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beynge moued to be spoken of in the Court of parlament, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating therof he being arriued at Paris for thys purpose, dyd in dede nothinge in it at al. And on thother side the bishop of Auxerre his hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde seruaunt, did so muche vnder hande by procuringe of fautors and secret handlynge, by giuinge secret intelligence to the presidentes, and some of the counsellors of the sayde parlament, of the determinations of the D. of Guise, that Thedict by this meanes was staied, from being verifyed. The prouost of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes at Paris, on thother side stirred by the same meane, together with certain factions merchauntes, dyd so muche by oppositions, wise, and goynge to and fro one in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers necke, that the second time he
<pb facs="tcp:12761:7"/>staied the said verification (wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the numbre of Church men hopes much) whiche made the third parte of the sayde Court of parlamente &amp; was framed in a maner altogether for the Popes appetit so as in thend the Edict could not be suffered to be verified, but by meanes of assistance geuen by my Lorde the Prince of la Roche Sur yon, sent by the king to this ende to the sayde Court, whose presence &amp; reuerence made the sayde oueropen partialitie, beinge in the sayde Court ashamed, whiche then was disseuered, and banished away to the greate confusion of thefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons partye.</p>
            <p>In this meane tyme the Duke of Guise ceased not on thother part to vse his practise in Sauarne a towne of almaine where he was, and pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed men of warre, to haue them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at nede. Seinge perfectlye that this enterprise could not be brought to passe, without force of Armes, so as the said house of Guise, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, and the Marshall S. Andre, perceyuing this Edict to be thus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed, to their great griefe, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure, he determined further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
<pb facs="tcp:12761:7"/>their first intentes and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, to come strong &amp; armed into the towne of Paris, and from thence to the kinges Court, to thintent they beinge first seased of the towne, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the persons of the king and Queene, they might then more easely execute their enterprise: and the Duke of Guise to geue a more honest color of his returne, procured that he shuld be sent so by the kinge of Nauarre, and that withoute the Quenes knowledge. The said Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable at the same tyme willinge to take occasion, to departe frome the Court discontented, hauing within a fewe dayes gone twise oute of the Court, at the last tyme entred in to so earnest a standing in words with the Quene, that she bare good wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the small respect he had to the honor and reuerence he bare towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des her. And as for the marshall S. Andre not satisfyinge himselfe with tharrogante refusuall made by him to go to his gouernment and charg, vpon the trust he reposed in his fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (by whom he perceiued himself upholden) he stode in termes before the counsaile with the sayde Lady,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:8"/>with such countenaunce and words as declared small obedience.</p>
            <p>Hauinge then brought foorth their enterprises thus farre forward, the Duke of Guise retourning from his iourney into Almain, to geue know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge firste of all others, the hostile enemite that he bare towardes reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which he minded to persecute, and all them also which woulde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the same, toke his way of a set pourpose throughe a Towne of Champaigne called Wassy, beinge informed that there was in the same a reformed Church: and beyng there arriued and accompanied with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine menne of warre he made there such and so cruel a bochery &amp; slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of poore people the kinges sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, that there were no fewer thē foure score personnes killed, and as many or more hurt, amonges whom ther were women and litle children altogether assembled withoute any weapons, to heare the Sermon, and to pray vnto god after their accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med fashion.</p>
            <p>The feare hereof being brought to paris, all men of one syde and other were greatly troubled, loking vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:8"/>that this was not but the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of a greate myschiefe, and streight waies the rumor was spred abroade euery where, that the D. of Guise came in armes with a greate company, with determination vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to supppresse all the reformed Churches. The which also for their partes, in consideracion, that it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the kinges Edict could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them against the violence &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their enemies, stode vpon their gard, hauing first sent to the Quene certain personages of al sorts, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Iustyce at her handes, for the murthers commytted at the sayds place of Wassy. The Quene beyng then come to Monceaux wyth the king in a maner alone. The king of Nauarre, the Mareshall S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, the Mareshall Brisac, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers being at Paris, whither sone after came y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Constable: Who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from his house thyther, wyth the hoole heires and of hys frendes and seruauntes, met (nere vnto S. Denis) the king and the Quene, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Monceaux, and withoute do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any duty to them, hastenyng to winne Paris, passed by theym as
<pb facs="tcp:12761:9"/>though he had costed by a company of vnknowen people, notwythstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng that Le Seigneur de Sansac, warned hym to stay, tellinge hym, Sir yonder is the king, the Consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble answering that he knew it well inough.</p>
            <p>Aboute this tyme, my Lorde the Prynce of Condee hauynge taken leue of the kynge and the Quene to go home to his house and being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued at Paris, desyring to prouyde for the daungers whiche threatned the towne, departed thence, vppon the Quens sending for him, to mete with the king and her at Monceaux where he toulde them that whyche he feared, and that to auoid the trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles it should be well done, that the sayde D. of Guise (who was repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to come with greate power and stronge hande, in contraryinge the kinges ordinances) at the lest might not passe through the towne of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, which aduice was well allowed by the Quene and the kinge of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre, and accordinge to the same, the sayde Lady wrote very expresse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Duke of Guise being then at hys house of Nantueil, prayinge
<pb facs="tcp:12761:9"/>him to come and mete the kynge at Monceaur, declaring vnto him, the desire she had to se him, and to feast him in her house. The sayd Duke of Guise sent worde vnto her, for aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, that he could not come to her for that he was busyed and letted in banquetting of his frendes whiche wer come to se hym. After warde the Quene hauinge againe written to the sayde Duke of Guise letters of the sentens, receyued no aunswers at all from him. But after he had interteined his frends, (in folowing the determinacion of thenterprise) tooke his waye to Paris, thoughe it were further of from him, then to goo meete the Kynge and the Quene at Monceaux, whyche was nerer hande.</p>
            <p>Thus the Duke of Guise accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the Constable, the D. Dammale, the Marshal S. Andre, &amp; others of Coūsail in their enterprise came into Paris by S. Denys gate, (though his right way were to haue entred by S. Martyns gate,) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge hys entrey in open armure, whiche was the state he kept conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallye, since hys dayes woorke at
<pb facs="tcp:12761:10"/>Wassy. And there assisted him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise at this entry the prouost of the Marchauntes, and thre of them Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuing against al custome, who (as he is a lighte and a factious person) went to receyue hym, wyth a verye greate company and with great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations made by people subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therunto, as if the king himself were entred in person, in so muche as they cried alowd, <hi rend="roman">God saue the Duke of Guise</hi> without that, (notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the said Duke or others of his company made any demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the same did at all mislike them: And immediatlye after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said D. of Guise was thus arriued &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued into the towne of Paris, the said Constable, the Marshal S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre &amp; the Marshall Brisac, began to bold daily a priuate counsail amōgs theym selues, forbearinge to call to theim the Prince of Condee, beinge there present with theim. Whyle these things were in hand, the king, the Quene, and the king of Nauarre remayninge as yet at Monceaux. The Quene (hauing had aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente from three places, that is to saye, from Portugall, Spayne, and
<pb facs="tcp:12761:10"/>Sauoy, of enterprise of the house of Guise, minding to sease then of the persons of the king and her, &amp; of all those things which she findeth true at this day: she determined to hasten her departure, &amp; to retire her self to some place of safety. And hauing im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parted her letters to the king of Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uarre, they departed from the saide place &amp; came to Melun, pourposyng to haue attained to Orleans: and sodenly there arriued the prouost of marchantes suborned for the nones, criyng vpon the Quene, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> if she reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Paris al was lost, saiyng y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Prince of Condee was ther with a great nūber of men, protesting, that al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euil which might happen shuld be turned vpon her, &amp; not vpon him, with manye other lyke foolishe and rashe deuises set forth then by him: So as though the said Lady be a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of singuler vertue and constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, beinge neuerthelesse put in feare of all sides, agreed to goo to Fontaniebleau: And the prouost of Marchantes hauinge thus farre wonne her, beganne to tell her, that the Cytyzens of the Towne
<pb facs="tcp:12761:11"/>of Paris were vnarmed, and that the Prince of Condee was then ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the said Citizens were in great daunger, and he dyd so much with her that he obtained, that their armure shuld be restored vnto them, whyche in deede were before taken from them, &amp; put within the towne house, to preuent troubles &amp; sturres which were before in the said town, and beganne again after they were restored. And furthermore the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the said prouost of Marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes was non other, but to strengthē the Duke of Guise alwayes in the towne, knowing wel that he would retire himselfe thither beynge ones feased of the persons of the king and Quene. The Prince of Condee was in thys meane tyme wythin the towne of Paris, wyth some whyche then were about hym, beyng kepte there at the request of diuerse of the reformed religion, who feared much the armed vyolence of the Duke of Guise and in deede hys presence dyd stay much, that there was no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and that the vulgar people, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che alreadye began to be puffed vp, wyth a vaine hope, vppon the D. of
<pb facs="tcp:12761:11"/>Guises comming, durst not execute or begin any folish enterprise. The towne hauing bene durynge hys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode there in great quiet and reste, they that came thither euil disposed, and durst not as then to vtter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, as in dede they did afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, when they saw they were alone and no more kepte backe with thys bridle &amp; seing that by meanes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they could not execute their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose neither at Paris nor elswhere, they did so much in thend, that they caused the king of Nauarre to come vnto them, vsing still the meanes of their prouost of Marchantes, which went to call vpon him, that his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence was nedeful at Paris for the daunger of vprores.</p>
            <p>The kinge of Nauarre beinge then arriued, the Duke of Guise and all his traine were verye glad, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge to kepe their counsaill as they did before, and causing the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ministers, presidentes, counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors &amp; officers of the towne to come vnto them, they made them tunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande that thys was in dede the kinges counsail, as kept by the chief officers of the Realme, and so they made their consultacions together
<pb facs="tcp:12761:12"/>without calling the saide Lorde the Prynce of Condee vnto theym, no more then they did before. Al which consultacions were greatlye suspec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, speciallye to men of honour and qualitie, who coulde not be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it was nedefull or lawful to kepe the same thus apart, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the counsail remaininge about the king and the Quene, and namely seing the said Lorde Prince was present there, and yet nothinge was com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>icated vnto him. Al those which had neuer so litle know ledge of the affaires iudged verily, that this was nothing elles, but a continuaunte of a practyse, whiche was framed a great while before, &amp; that which didde the more confirme this opinion, was the discontenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion which was well knowne to be in theym of the house of Guyse the Constable, &amp; the Marshal S. Audre, wherof we haue spoken here before.</p>
            <p>The chief ende of all these coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selles was, to make themselues wel assured of the towne of Paris, and to driue the Prince of Cōdee out of the same, as he which muche hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their enterprise: To go and sease
<pb facs="tcp:12761:12"/>theimselues of the personnes of the kinge and the Quéene, and after to bringe theym into the saide towne, wherby hauinge thone and thother at their cōmaundement, they might there the better bring to passe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of their enterprise. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as the presence of the sayde Lorde the Prince, did greatly offend the Duke of Guise, not willinge to go out of the towne so longe as the Prince shoulde be there, notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng that in comming to Paris he caused it to bee bruited that he would not lye there but one nyght, he deuised to cause a report to goo, that the said Prince was at Parys accompanied with a greate number of gentelmen, &amp; that the towne fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe to be sacked had praied him to tary for the defence of it. Which the Prince vnderstandynge, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all occasion of malicious suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion falslye deuised, offered inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to the Cardinall of Burbon deputed as then gouernoure of the town of Paris, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was readye to go forth of one of the gates, when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> D. of Guise shuld go out at an other. The Marshal Montmorency y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right
<pb facs="tcp:12761:13"/>gouernoure of the towne then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge dyscharged, at the instigacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the prouost of Marchauntes, as one whom he thought to wise &amp; considerate for to endure his facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and suborned sedicions.</p>
            <p>But the Duke of Guise hauynge refused to accept this office, the said Lord Prince, being aduertised that the Quene desired that they should depart of thone syde and that her, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> for this cause, the king of Nauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was come to Paris, was so rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; so willing tobey this cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that albeit he had bene sick in hys bed twoo dayes together, he staid not for al that readily to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himself with all his company, drawing streight home to his house of La Feate, with mind to sende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way al his company, if the Duke of Guise had done the like. But the Duke of Guise hauinge that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired went in such furniture of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure as he was, to mete with oure yong kinge, and the Quene his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Fontainbleau, where seinge her self, on al sides, compassed about to armes and force against her wil, &amp; expresse cōmaundement, she found herself in great feare.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:13"/>
            <p>In this meane season the Prouost of marchauntes, desirous too make the towne of Paris well assured to the deuotion of the house of Guyse, leued immediatly the number of .xv hundreth men for the garde therof, withoute any assēble of the towns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or determination of thē, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon first made. Wheras before he had (as farrefoorth as he could) refu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed to receyue onely three hundreth men, appointed by the Kyng to the sayde Marshall Montmorency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge gouernour. And the same refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall made, after many assembles of the towne called to this ende, alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge as then that it was againste the priuileges and franchises of the same, not hauinge bene accustomed to haue any other garde thenne the garde of the burgeses, and with the number of fiftene hundreth menne, thus established by him, he gaue fre libertie too the citiezens to furnishe theym selfe, and vse those weapons whiche had ben restored vnto them, whiche thing was executed w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> such and insolency by the vulgare peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as it semed too bee a frontiere towne in the time of hostilita, seing
<pb facs="tcp:12761:14"/>that there was nothinge sene nor heard of all sides, but weapons and artillary together with many rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries and outrages, specially done vpon them, whiche were of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (whiche they call new) goinge or cominge frome thassemblies, too serue God and to heare his woorde, in such sort as the Marshal de Lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, willinge one daye to stay such force, was there him selfe in greate hasard of his person, and coulde not so prouide, but that ther were forth within his presence fyue or six mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders committed, his own folkes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured, without that any iustice hath therof ben done, no more thē was of other violēces perpetrated through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fury of the people. For the duke of Guise and the Cōstable them selfs, who came after to Paris, sente for the Prouost of the sayde lorde Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal, and afterward for the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant crimines of the same town, to whome (with sore threatnings, and castinge of them in feare) they gaue very expresse commaundement, too suppresse thinformatiōs of the cause whiche they hadde before them, and
<pb facs="tcp:12761:14"/>to set those at libertye, whome they had enprisonned.</p>
            <p>It happened that the sayde lorde prince hauing ben at his house, toke his waye for to returne to the court as he had promised to doe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the feast of Easter, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the house of Guise hauinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode, sende woorde foorth with to the Prouost of the marchauntes, to stande vppon his garde, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to let, that the sayde Prince shoulde not entre into the towne. Wherein suche diligence was vsed by the sayde Prouost, that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atlye, and without further assemble of the towne (as he is wont to do) he signified to all the quartermaisters of the towne, to goe &amp; warne all the houses of the same, that euery man shoulde be in a readines, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hauing caused all the barre chaynes of the towne to be drawen (whiche hathe not bene accustomed nor sene too bee done, but in tyme of hostilitie and greate daunger, and whenne the ennemye appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth) hee armeth hym selfe: and
<pb facs="tcp:12761:15"/>&amp; accompanied with all the archers and harquebousiers, and many mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chauntes of the towne of Paris, he made his muster in the same: and as the said lorde Prince passed by, nere Paris, with those whiche accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him, going to lodge that night at sainct Cloud, and thinkinge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge lesse then to desire too entre into the sayd towne, the Prouost of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> marchaunts caused ordinaunce to be continually shot of, in such sorte as there is no remembraunce, that there hath suche a stirre ben sene in the saide towne these hundreth yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; more, what daunger of warre soeuer hath happened in this realm.</p>
            <p>Assone as the saide house of Guise vnderstoode, that the saide lorde the Prince drew streight towardes the court, well considering that his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence in that place should not be for their furtheraunce, and would lette them to bringe awaye the king and the Queene to the towne of Paris, to haue thone and thother in theyr power, accordinge too their first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise: euen sodenly abusing the king of Nauarres authorite, whom they had &amp; yet haue altogether on theyr
<pb facs="tcp:12761:15"/>side, did so much as he came streight to tell the Queene, that she must de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte from Fontainebleau, for the suertie of the Kinges person, layng maliciously too the Princes charge that he woulde come to sease of the Kinges person. Whiche the Quene streighte hereuppon woulde haue dissuaded vnto the king of Nauarre declaringe vnto him that it was no meanes credible, beinge greatelye amased with this matter: The king also sayinge that he woulde not go from Fontainbleau. But the sayde kynge of Nauarre, thrust forwarde by the saide house of Guyse, whoe sawe that otherwise their purpose was brooken, spake againe too the sayde Ladye, sayinge that she muste nedes departe, and that hee went to take the Kynge, and that she should folowe after if she wold. Approchinge then in this sort to the persone of the Kyng, who was we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge with the Quene his mother. they hastened him forward so well, as w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> in a little whyle, they brought hym into the towne of Melun, wher they lodged him within the Castle, in the whiche no kinge had lodged
<pb facs="tcp:12761:16"/>these hūdreth years, nor any others, but suche as haue ben wont too bee sent thither prisoners.</p>
            <p>My lord the prince vnderstanding this news, perceiuing that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the saide lorde of Guise, was plainely ynough, declared too the woorlde (though before manye doubted thereof) wayinge that he was a prince of the bloud, and that by the lawe of nature it apertayned vnto him to defende the kyngs sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, and namely to resist suche as woulde oppresse theym by force and violēce: thought best for his sauety to return him self to Orleans, and from thence to geue all the kynges subiects to vnderstand his meaning &amp; desire, to preuent the Imminent daunger, which hanged ouer theym all, to thintent they wold assist him to restore the person of the king, the Queene, &amp; the duke of Orleans too liberty, and to maintaine the kings edicts in their force and strength.</p>
            <p>The house of Guise this meane tyme, perceiuinge the saide Prince to be retired from them, but not too suche a place, as they woulde haue wished, too haue better inioyed his company, beganne more ouertly to
<pb facs="tcp:12761:16"/>execute their enterprise, causing the kynge of Nauarre to tel the Quene that she must go to Paris, albeit the Kinge spake of nothing elles but of his return to Fontainebleau, &amp; ces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not to wepe with the queene his mother, seinge euidently their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuite, &amp; specially the Queene whoe sawe that happen, which was decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto her, too the greate grief of his obedient subiects and seruaūts. And so muche was done by the help of the Prouost of merchaunts, who eftsones persisted to sende woorde, that the presence of the kynge was nedeful at Paris, so as being resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the morninge to goe to Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainebleau, after dynner immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely the purpose was altered to goe to Paris.</p>
            <p>The Constable hauing knowledge of thys resolution, toke vpō him to be one of the first at Paris, to begin to execute their enterprisemēt to be done, throughoute al the townes of this realme, as sithēs theffects whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue folowed, haue geuē mē tū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande, &amp; that with the greatest terror and strikinge of a feare in to men that he coulde in suche sorte, as departing from Melun at one of the
<pb facs="tcp:12761:17"/>clocke at after noone, accompanied with two hundreth horses or more, al furnished with ii. or. iii. pistolets, entred into the sayde towne aboute eight of the clocke at night, and the next morninge very early he wente without any charge or commission to apprehēde monsieur de Ruze, an aduocate in the court of parlamēt, who asking him by what authorite, he maide him prysoner, &amp; for what cause, he had no aunswer but these woordes: Content your selfe, that I am Constable: for in dede he doeth pretende, that withoute other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission or commaundemēt, he hath power to commaunde in thabsence of the kynge, and the kynge of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre, whatsoeuer he should thinke good, as he spake aloude too all the worlde: doinge all thinges in suche rage, as is incredible to many.</p>
            <p>The sayde Ruze, hauinge bene thus taken and sent prysoner to the Bastille, within a very straict pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, for what cause no man as yet knoweth (oneles it be for that he is one of them, whiche did mooste fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and fauour openly the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med religiō) he went forth with one
<pb facs="tcp:12761:17"/>of the Towne to a house named the Temple of Ierusalem, nere S. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes gate (in which place the assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and preaching was made) where he caused to be plucked downe, and throwne to thearth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pulpit wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they preached, and certain seates and stooles whiche were there, and the same heaped altogether, caused it to be set on fire, beinge assisted wyth a verye greate number of the Vulgar people, which blessed hym, and praised him very highly, to see him do so vertuous, and so worthy a dede, for a Constable of Fraūce, the said Constable saiyng openlye, that there must be no more such assēblies within this Realm, &amp; that the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers must nedes retire them selues thence, and that there shoulde be an Edict published to that ende. From thens he went to doe asmuche after diner, in an other howse when also thassēblies were made named Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incourt, which is withoute S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonyes gate: and there waited vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, yea more then before, by the vulgar sorte, after he had caused the Pulpyt to be throwne downe, and
<pb facs="tcp:12761:18"/>the seates and it to be laid together he did the lyke of that he did, at the other house, so as the people seynge thēselfs so much made of by a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable of Fraunce, euen as though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had bene in a maner their felow; they were so wel kindled, as not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied to haue set on fire the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits and seates, they tooke boldnes forthwith (the said Constable being present and consentinge) to sette on fire the house which was great and wide, so as now it is razed to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye grounde.</p>
            <p>And this vulgar people foolish and mad by meanes of the familiaritys shewed theym by the Constable, not yet satisfied, through the general li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye giuen to all menne to weare weapons at the becke and commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the prouost of Merchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: that .iiii. or .v. dais together ther was nothing hard and spoken of but murthers, robberies, pillages, and open iniuries vsed by the people vpō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> next vnto thē, of what quality so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they were, if they had bene in neuer so litel suspicyon of religiō, &amp; there was not so honest a man, that in passing by the streates (if he were
<pb facs="tcp:12761:18"/>in the least suspicion that coulde be trew or false for the same religion) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was not iniured &amp; outraged, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man hauing full liberty to carye pistolettes in the streates, insomuch as of all sides there was nothynge heard but continual noise of shot.</p>
            <p>Sone after the comminge of the Constable, the king and the Quene were brought to Boys de Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and euen after the next morow the said house of Guise, because that place was not stronge ynoughe for their pourpose, caused the kynge to hasten his entry, because they wold lodge him in the castle of the Louure as the place whyche they tooke to be mooste safe for theym. Suche an entree beynge made after a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on not accustomed &amp; with the dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing of the kings greatnes, euen amonges straunge nacions; whiche was done, for that they supposed hereby to hide the knowledge of the kinges fowle captiuity, wherin thei do miserablye retaine hys maiestye: And to keepe hym in a place more assured for their deuocion, fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth hereuppon they beganne to
<pb facs="tcp:12761:19"/>deuise to make open warre vpon the said Lord Prince, &amp; meaning to take counsail therein together, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable said to the L. Chaūcelor, who was there presente in the kynges chamber, that this busynes belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not but to suche as be exercised u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> armes, to whom the sayde Lorde Chauncelor said, that albeit he and those of his coore were not skilled in handlynge of weapons, yet for all that they coulde tell well inoughe, when they are to be vsed, and not to be vsed, neuertheles forasmuche as then (as also it is presently) all was done with force, and open violence, he was kept from theim alofe, as he hath bene alwayes sythens, and to be the more assured of themselues in all thinges, namely to haue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings counsail at their commaundement, thei made therof by their own authority, those of whō thei thought they might make sore accoumpt as <hi rend="roman">le sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneur de Boily</hi> maister of the horse, the Court villars, being kinsemen, and allyed with the saide Constable, <hi rend="roman">le seigneur de Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a verye affectionate seruaunte to the said house of Guise and the Constable, <hi rend="roman">le seigneur Descars,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12761:19"/>and the Bishop of Auxerre houshold seruauntes to the king of Nauarre, and whose meanes the sayd house of Guise do vse, specially to go aboute at their secret practises, and put out those whom they sawe prefar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the common wealth, before their: owne priuate passion.</p>
            <p>But to retourne to their counsels and executyons of the same, the house of Guise hauing vnderstanded the protestacyon and declaratyon made on the said L. the Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and sent to the king, the effect whereof was, that he not sturred with anye partyculer affection, but rather with the duty and onely loue whiche he particularlye bare to the crown, vnder the gouernment of the Queene, he had bene constrayned to enter into armes, to restore the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone of the kinge and the Quene, to their ful libertye, and to maintaine thobseruacion of the kings maiesties Edictes and ordenances, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the last touchinge the cause of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, offeringe to retourne to his house, if the D. of Guise woulde doe the like.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:20"/>
            <p>Thei hauing then perceiued this de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claration, and seing there were two points which they must finely cloke and couer, that is to wit, the kinges captiuity, and the countermandinge of the diet of Ianuary they procured in all haste thexpedicion of a letter theight of Aprill last paste, whereby the king declared, that the bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of his captiuitye is a false and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true sklaunder, inuented by the said lord the Prince therby to excuse him self of his doynges, declarynge that the Quene and he were in such ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye as they haue euer bene, &amp; as they coulde wyshe, and that he and the saide Ladye came of their owne mindes, into the saide towne of Paris to prouide for and to remedy the troubles happened.</p>
            <p>And the Court of Parlament was sent vnto, to reade and publysh the said letters, which was done so rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilye or rather all hedlonge, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste all custome, that (beynge brought to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Chamber of plees, and whiles that men were playdinge of matters, they were incontynentlye delyuered to the kynges mynysters and the publication therof required
<pb facs="tcp:12761:20"/>at their handes) euen in one instant, it was ordered that they shoulde be redde, published, and inregistred▪ Streight after, callinge to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce vpon a sodayne a more sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll wile and craft, in causing other letters of the xii. day folowing to be couched, whereby it is declared that the said lorde Prince, vnder a faulse and counterfait colour of religion, was seased in hys persone, by some sedicious persones, which kept him in their handes.</p>
            <p>And to mete with thother, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point purported by the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyon made by the sayde Lorde Prince, touching the matter of rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they cause other letters of the xi. of the same moneth to be dispat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, wherby the kinge geueth tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande, that he is informed, that diuerse haue retired theim selues to Orleauns (assembled in great num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers) and to other places, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of a feare whiche they saye they haue, that their consciences shalbe searched, and that they shalbe staide from the vsynge of Thedyctes and ordenances made by him, namely in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> last moneth of Ianuary, touching
<pb facs="tcp:12761:21"/>the matter of religion, and to vexe and trouble theym for the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion whyche they holde. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth by the same, that to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all feare and doubte, he hath not ment to call the sayde Edyct to question, neyther that anye shuld be touchinge the cause of religion mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested, except the Towne of Paris, Faulxbourges, and Baylywike of the same, wherin the sayd kynge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, that he will not haue anye publike or priuate assēblies made, nor anye adminystration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in other sorte, then as hath beene receyued and obserued in the Church of Roome. Which letters beinge presented in the saide Court by the saide Duke of Guise and the Constable, albeit they were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to Thedict of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, whiche is generall for all the townes, yet are they redde, publys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and enrolled, wherunto the said Court added, that the said rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and publication made by the same, is, in respect of the present ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessytye of the tyme, and as it were only by waye of a prouision, &amp; vntil suche time as it be otherwise proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:12761:21"/>which discouereth sufficiently y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the meaning of the said Court, and the D. of Guise is all one, that is, to make frustrate the last Edict of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, in kepinge too their vse the chiefe towne, like as the saide D. of Guise did at that time euedently de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare in the sayde Court: So as yet further, the matter was made more apparaūt by other letters depeched at the same tyme: By the which the kynge declareth, that he meaneth not that the saide Edict take place, but in the townes, where the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers were already established, and not in the rest. Whiche were in this sort sent foorth, partly too serue for an occasion, to make the cruell and horrible slaughter, whiche folowed soone after in the towne of Sens, where against all huminite a great number of people were killed, besi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des great robberies and sackinge of houses, whiche continued two dais together, and not without great sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piciō, against the cardinal of Guise, archebishop there, and of his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and seruaunts. Which is the sūme of all that I haue ben able too gather of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> whiche hath happened
<pb facs="tcp:12761:22"/>hitherto, couering the present trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and controuersie, beinge in thys realme, and for whiche euery man in thesame is in armes.</p>
            <p>It resteth now to gyue tunderstād by degrees all the reasons wherew<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thone side &amp; thother may help them selfs, to cause al men more perfectly knowe whiche of the twoo is better grounded, &amp; may be said to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into armes with best righte of their side. We haue now sene howe the house of Guise, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōstable &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shal s. Andre, withdrew them selfes frō the Courte one after another, &amp; the smal regard they haue had to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Quene, sithens they haue felt them self backt with the king of Nauarre &amp; how their best &amp; chief pretext hath alwayes ben, that they do arme thē selfs to maintayne the Catholique religion. Takinge occasion to finde faulte with the gouermente of the realme: charginge the Quene much for her owne greate lenite and soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the Kynges counsayl, for win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge at thinges, and the magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for their negligence, and aboue all thinges complayning of the last
<pb facs="tcp:12761:22"/>Edict of Ianuary. We haue also sene the beginning, procedinge, and ende of their ētreprice, alwaies gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by violence and strong hand, by murthers and shedding of bloude, &amp; by disobeinge the Queenes expresse cōmaundements: &amp; next their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sail deuided frō the king. The solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations, stirres, &amp; tumultes raised in the towne of Paris, by suche as were suborned, &amp; by making muche of the people, seruing much to theyr purpose. And lastly the seasinge of the kyng and Quenes persons, the pressinge of the Kynges counsaill &amp; to his officers of iustice, hauing eue violently extorted, and in dede veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied one lettre in an others necke, cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to custome and the Edicts.</p>
            <p>On the prince of Condee his side, we see too the contrary, hys goinge frome the Courte with the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fauoure, and with promisse too retourne thyther foorthwyth.</p>
            <p>We see hys abode at Parys too haue bene quiet, and requisite to staye the styrres, which were there towards. And next his ready obeing of the Quenes commaundementes,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:23"/>although it had ben more fette for the D. of Guise first to haue obeyed the same. The outrage and iniurie done to the sayde lorde by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uost of the marchaunts, as if it had ben to an enemy of the croune, born neuerthelesse paciently by the sayde prince. His returninge to Orleans for the sauety of his persone, and of his, after that the Kinge &amp; Quenes captiuitie, was verye openlye dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered. And lastely the declaration of the cause that moued him too entre into armes, sente by hym too the kynge, with offer to retire him selfe, and to lay doune his force, so as the house of Guise would doe the like, the kinges Edicts remayninge in their force.</p>
            <p>So as there is none, that seeth not clearly on the one part all obediēce to the Queene, and on thother side disobedience towardes the same.</p>
            <p>That thone side tooke weapon in hande to offende, and thother to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende. The violence of thone, and the withstanding therof in thother. Thone meaning to subuert y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings law by force, &amp; of his own auctorite. Thother as a prince of the bloude,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:23"/>&amp; one of the Protectors of the lawes of Fraunce, mynded to maintaine the same: and consequently the one continuinge hys duety, and thother setled in the doing of wronge. For what greate matter is it, that the house of Guise can pretend, to touch then, by retiring of themselfs, and to lay doune their force, seinge that my lorde the Prince is contended so to do? What reason can they alledg for them selfs, to minde of thē selfs, to disanull that which the Estates haue so earnestly required, and the Kinge by suche departe of counsaill hath graunted? If they say, thei wil defend the Churche of Rome, whoe is it that hindereth them to do it?</p>
            <p>Doeth any man se the Bishops and Curates, driuen frome their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, doeth any see them staide from preachinge, and too doe that whiche good and faithfull ministers ought to do? Or elles is it not, than they beare malice to them of the religion (whiche they call newe) to see them do so well, as to be driuē out of the townes, as men infected with lepre or pestilence, setfoorthe to the raine and wynde, and in the contempte of
<pb facs="tcp:12761:24"/>euery man? Are there so many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten people, which abide the Iewes in their townes, &amp; namely the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes holines, doth suffer them in hys chief town, and els where: and shall not those whiche confesse the name of Iesu Christe, as he in whom they beleue is onely their saluation, doe beleue &amp; suffer for his Gospell sake, finde a place in Fraunce too retire them selfes to?</p>
            <p>Yea, but forsoth (say they) Is this a dede of a good religiō, to take pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the kinges townes &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, too entre into armes, withoute his leaue and licence, and too kepe backe the money groynge of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue? I woulde willingly aske the question, before I aūswer them, Is it a token of good religion, too pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse them selfs of the Kyng &amp; Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes persones, and of the chief town of hys Realme, of all hys force, aucthoritie, and substaunce, too em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye the same, to the thinfringing of hys Edicts, too oppresse his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, and subuert hys estate, and too thys ende too vse the ayde of straungers, seing the subiectes will not cōsent to so manifest a tyranny?
<pb facs="tcp:12761:24"/>See then I prai you, how quick wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted we are in other mens cases, and blinded in oure owne. Nowe I saye then to aunswer theym, that is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for my lorde the Prince, as a Prince of the bloude, a counsailor borne, and one of the Protectors of the croune, euen to whome by lawe of nature appertayneth the defence of the subiectes, when some woulde by violence oppresse them, to resiste therto by dynt of swearde, whiche God too this ende hath putte in hys handes, and consequently to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lawes and Edictes of the Realme. And touchinge the townes &amp; places, wherof they complaine, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the sayde lord Prince is s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ased: hath the kinge found him selfe any worse serued &amp; obeyed, then he hathe bene heretofore, and hathe there ben any alteration perceiued, but onely that they do arme them selfes, not myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to submitte them selfes to the violente oppression of the house of Guise, And touchynge the money deteyned, I desire too knowe, wherein a manne shoulde blayme hym, whoe hathe taken a knyfe oute of a madde mannes handes,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:25"/>If then my lorde the Prince, mente to staye that the house of Guise doe not abuse the Kinges treasure, too cause straungers too entre into hys realme, and oppresse his subiectes, wherein is he to be reproued?</p>
            <p>But to dilate yet somwhat further, and by degrees their reasons, not willinge to omit any one of theym, if it were possible, I woulde wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly aske them, by what meanes it is, that they mynde to defende the Romish religion; for the which they declare themselfes so well minded? It is by force, saye they, in driuinge awai the ministers out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> realme, in takinge awaie thassemblies, and puttinge to death the chiefest of the contrary religion; accordinge to the example of the sedition of Xantonge and of Bourdeaux, withoute anye searchinge of mens consciences, soo that they conteyne them selfs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their houses, and make no shewe thereof abrode. I can not ynoughe meruail of suche a counsail, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise, altogether contrarye, too that whiche they thē selfs, euen the very house of Guise it self, I saie (hauing at that time in their handes, in the tyme
<pb facs="tcp:12761:25"/>of the last king Fraunces the hoole gouernment of the Realme) caused to be published by letters and Edic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: and at such time as the number of theym whom they persecute, and persecuted before was a great deale fewer, and muche more easye to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse by force then they be nowe.</p>
            <p>For they were of opinion, that all rigor should ceasse, (as a thinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for the age of a yonge kinge, and vnsemely, wherupon his comyng to the croune of Fraūce, should be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to hys posteritye to haue bene bloudye) &amp; that troubles and diuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should be ended, by conuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the cleargie of the Realme, &amp; thither to call and admitte al sortes of people that woulde come to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone any thinges for the matter of religion, which purpose hauing ben broken by the death of the late laste kinge was executed in thys kynges reigne, in continuyng of that which by theimselues was thought good, and sythens confirmed by thaduyse of all the Prynces of the bloude, Cardinalles and others of the priuy counsayl assembled in the Courte of Parliament.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12761:26"/>
            <p>The house of Guise they hauyng sene that this way could do no good (and some know wherfore) and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing theym selues perceiued made and so often repeted by thestates, to thend to haue Temples, and being knowen, that the Quene left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vndone to finde some good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye, was in thende driuen to the remedy of thedict made in Ianuary last, by the aduise of the moste hable and sufficient men of this Realme, as the best and mooste commodious meanes, it is a marueilous matter to see that they are neuertheles eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones come to set forwarde the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of force, and in dede they haue taken the same in hand: as thoughe thei had already forgottē what good it did them, when they wente from Paris to Orleans, enuironned with menne of warre, euen like as if they had bene in thenemies countrye and vnder color of a conspiracy made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste the late last kinge, who by reason of his youth and good nature had neuer done any manne dysplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
            <p>And if it so be that thexamples of
<pb facs="tcp:12761:26"/>the tyme paste, and speciallye of the Arrians, Nouatins, and Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens (to whom for the selfe same rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons Temples were geuen, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times without and somtimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the townes) cannot serue at al to moue vs, to tollerate the lyke, that yet at the least they whome we haue sene before our eyes, may haue this power giuen them, to make vs wiser for the time to come? haue we not sene in Almaine as muche trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the same matter of religion and more then we be? and coulde one wyshe more carefullnesse, wisedome, and force then was in Themperour Charles the fyfth, worthy indede to be placed amongst the greatest, &amp; yet there is none of vs who hath not seene before his eyes, that all that coulde doe no good to appease the troubles for relygyon, till that he was at laste contented to graunte an Interim, synce the whyche the Countrey of Almayne was neuer seene in greater peace and quietnes hath the waye of force &amp; rigor serued to any great purpose
<pb facs="tcp:12761:27"/>in the realme of Englande? and too proceade to the realme of Scotland in what daunger haue we seene it, some thinking by the self same house of Guise reigning then in Fraunce, to do those thinges then which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentlye they haue eftsones begonne here: What reason is it then to say, that it is by force y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we must maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Catholike relygion, in dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing away the Mynisters (say they) oute of the Realme, as if that there were not a millyon euen amonges them that heare them (if a man may thus call them sufficient) to execute thoffice and charge of a minister.</p>
            <p>But their ignoraunce and rashnes doeth yet declare it selfe forther by thother point which they set forthe, making comparison of a trouble in religion with a matter of a popular sedicion. In the which they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel and be armed against the Prince at the very time that they are moste sedicious, they acknoweledge their fault in their conscience. And those which do stirre for the matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they are so farre of from thoughte of euill doynge, that they
<pb facs="tcp:12761:27"/>woulde for nothing hurt any man, nor therby to contrary the duetye of good and faithfull subiectes toward their kinge and liege lorde: So as it appereth that this is a foolyshe and vnaduised opinyon, to thynke that when the heades be dispatched, that it should be easy to brynge thothers back again, which oftentymes shew them as steadfast &amp; constant, &amp; their heades and conductour. And yet is it lesse wyt and reason, to saye that whiche they adde further, as it were wyth great prudence intermingled with lenitye, that is that they wyll not search mens conscyences so that euery one wil kepe himself at home. For besides that it is impossible to do it, as they do better vnderstād it, then thothers know it: there should not be a better meane to take away al discipline, and reuerence of God from amongst menne, and in thende to aboundaunce them to all libertye of vyce, beinge necessarye that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans relygyon be ordered and witnessed publiquely.</p>
            <p>Yea but (saye they) oure realme canne not indure twoo religions. We see the contrarye in the moste
<pb facs="tcp:12761:28"/>parte of Europe, thys beynge no perticuler disease of this Realme. Wherefore then maye not they well suffer the like? There is not one of eyther of the religions, but woulde wyshe there were but one of them.</p>
            <p>But seinge it is thus happened, yet must the best meanes be deuised and we become wise at the leaste by thexample of others, yea but (saye they agayne) yf that take place, the new religion will dailye encrease, &amp; in thend wil come to destroy ours. See here a good beginnynge of the distrust they haue of the goodnes of their religiō: For if it be of God, we muste not doubte, but it wyll sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount thother, and that it shal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p>But that whyche causeth them to saye so, is thexample they haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies, of the force of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (which they call new) whiche thoughe it be but poore, abiecte and neglected of all menne, hath not let notwithstandinge in a fewe yeares, to embrace almoste al Europe, and to ouercome and haue the vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande of armure, for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb facs="tcp:12761:28"/>of Emperours, and Kynges, the pompe, riches, pride, &amp; the height of Popes, Cardynalles, and al their followers. I desire to knowe for thys pourpose, if the Iuishe religion thoughe it haue beene suffered in Chrystendome more then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeares, hathe therfore destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and hyndered the Christian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Thus the whole beinge wel dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed, and ripely waied, there is great apparance, that it is not zeale of conscience, whiche pusheth theym forwarde, who declare theym selfe so well affected to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myshe relygyon, hauynge spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye thys marke to shoote at be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, to possesse them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues of the gouernemente of the Realme, and if they coulde of the Crowne it selfe and all vnder the visour and cloke of the Kynge of Nauarre, by vsynge hym to serue their tourne, afterwards to oppresse hym, and enter into hys place, and (to comme to thys ende) they ayde theym selues wyth a cloke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb facs="tcp:12761:29"/>meaninge too maintaine the Popes aucthoritie, whiche serueth their tournes so well vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour therof, and nothinge lesse, then to haue an eye too the peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, and quiet of the subiectes: In suche sort, as he that would saye at one woorde, that this is the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes warre, shoulde not perhaps bee very farre from the truthe.</p>
            <p>This hauinge ben alwayes the forme and maner of his holines, procedinge in mater of religion, and of al his ministres suborned by him to raise vp warres, thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine men by force, to raūge them selfs to his church, like as contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, the waye of the Gospell hathe ben, to bringe men of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, through preaching the woord of God vnto them.</p>
            <p>And we shall see in thende, which of the two wayes shalbe founde the best. They shal perceiue, how much they, with whome they haue to do, are bounde, ioyned, &amp; vnited toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and stedfaste and constante in their opinion. How many thousand amonges theym, doe make no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie
<pb facs="tcp:12761:29"/>to lose their goods, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye then to chaunge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse the doctrine, whiche they haue receiued. And they shall agayne knowe, that to gayn them by force, they must cause them all to dye, for that otherwise, he that shall remain or liue, with the asshes of them that shall dye, wil cause others to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. Iudge you whether it be not a fayre and goodly entreprice, to haue called in straungers, vtterly too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguishe the floure of Fraunce, &amp; to set the realm in a praye. O mō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struous vnfaithfulnes, worthy to be assailed by all men, as a wyld beast. To call (I saye) straungers to settle oure controuersies, &amp; to gyue vntoo them the places of thē, which shal be ouercomen, and to kepe him vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote, to whome there shal remaine but the name of a victor.</p>
            <p>And nowe too make an ende, it nedeth not (as I take it) too excuse my lord the Prince of that, that his aduersaries woulde maliciouslye impute vnto him, iudging his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, accordinge too their owne. Sayinge: that this is not (as it is
<pb facs="tcp:12761:30"/>not in dede for their parte) the zeale of religion that moued hym. And that hys griefe is in an other place, procedinge of some affection of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, reuenge or ambition. If the sayde lorde the Prince hadde not already gyuen me sufficientlye tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande, that he is nothinge lesse then vindicatif, and that accordinge to the profession, whiche he maketh of the Gospel, he hath remitted all reuenge to God, he woulde not denye but that the house of Guyse hath geuen hym sufficient occasion, to enter into this desire of reuenge. And as touching the matter of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, they them selfes knowe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter howe he hath liued heretofore, and howe hee is increased in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce, and that if he were alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether distempered (as they be) with this thursting after goods, aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and greatnes, that it is longe of none, but of hym selfe that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same is not quenched.</p>
            <p>And (to make an ende) you haue here the discours by degrees, of the cōtrouersy happened in this realme and the causes and reasons, that
<pb facs="tcp:12761:30"/>maye be alledged of thone side and thother, too haue moued eyther of the partyes, too haue entred into armes. Nowe resteth it in euery subiectes choyse, or anye other, hauing desire to stirre, to the partakyng with thone or thother, too iudge since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relye, and without passion, to whiche of the twoo parties hee shall do best to ioyn hym selfe.</p>
            <trailer>¶FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>